<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nature of God's kingdom and dominion over men clearly laid open and explained, as the same relates to these following particulars ... in a discourse on Deut. 8.2. wherein is likewise shewed, what influence these things ought to have upon our life and conversation / by Richard Stafford.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93746</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42792</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875760</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875760</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152398</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93746)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152398)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2295:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nature of God's kingdom and dominion over men clearly laid open and explained, as the same relates to these following particulars ... in a discourse on Deut. 8.2. wherein is likewise shewed, what influence these things ought to have upon our life and conversation / by Richard Stafford.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by E. Whitlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 40.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Deuteronomy VIII, 2 --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Kingdom of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152398:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NATURE OF <hi>God's Kingdom</hi> AND Dominion over MEN, Clearly laid Open and Explained, as the ſame Relates unto theſe following Particulars. God hath Eſtabliſhed for all Nations an Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Faith, a Life of Probation and Trial, wherein all things happen alike unto all. He hath alſo Permitted the Proſperity of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Ordained Adverſity unto the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            <p>IN A Diſcourſe on <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. 2. Wherein is likewiſe ſhewed, what Influence the Knowledge of theſe things ought to have upon our Life and Converſation.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD STAFFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>To make known unto the Sons of Men, his Mighty Acts and the Glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of his Kingdom. Thy Kingdom is an Everlaſting Kingdom, and thy Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion endureth throughout all Generations,</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſal. 145. 12, 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>And thou ſhalt Remember all the Way which the Lord thy God led thee theſe Forty Years, to Prove thee, to know what is in thine Heart, whither thou wouldeſt keep his Commandments or no.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Nihil tam dignum Deo, quam Salus Hominis.</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and Sold By <hi>E. Whitlock,</hi> near <hi>Stationers Hall</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:152398:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THeſe are to give Notice, that I have ſeveral other Practical Sermons or Diſcourſes of mine own Compoſing, Lying by me in Manuſcript; Which if they, who have the Plenty or Competency of this World, would thus <hi>Conſecrate</hi> ſome part of their <hi>Gain</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance unto the Lord,</hi> Micah 4. 13. As to be <hi>ready to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute</hi> and <hi>willing to Communicate</hi> towards the outward Labour and Charge of the Printing and Publiſhing of them, it would be for the Glory of God (in <hi>making known his Truth,</hi> Iſa. 38. 19.) and for the Edification and Benefit of his Church and People; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it would be a <hi>Good Work</hi> in ſuch Perſons, who ſhall be Helpful and any ways Aſſiſtant herein; for which they would be Rewarded by God in the Life that is to come.</p>
            <p>Charge them that are Rich in this World, that they do Good, that they be Rich in good Works, ready to Diſtribute, willing to Communicate, laying up in Store for themſelves a good Foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on Eternal Life, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 17, 18, 19. This is a Faithful Saying, and theſe things I will that thou affirm conſtantly, that they which have believed in God, might be careful to maintain good Works; theſe things are Good and Profitable unto Men, <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 8.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152398:2"/>
            <head>THE NATURE OF <hi>God's Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>And thou ſhalt Remember all the Way which the Lord thy God led thee theſe Fourty Years in the Wilderneſs, to Humble thee, and to Prove thee, to know what was in thine Heart, whither thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt keep his Commandments or no,</q>
               <bibl>Deut. 8. 2.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE whole O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>conomy, Diſpenſation and Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of all the Things of God, and of the Things pertaining to his Kingdom, in that manner as they now are, do all ſeem to be to this very End and Intent, to <hi>prove Man,</hi> to <hi>know what is in his Heart, whether he will keep the Commandments of God or not.</hi> This alſo cometh from the Lord of Hoſts, who is Wonderful in Counſel, and Excellent in Working; for in great Wiſdom and Contrivance hath he Ordained and Ordered Things accordingly. By the Paſſage of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> through the Wilderneſs, was tipi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ied and ſignified that Paſſage of the ſeveral Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Men and Women of the ſeveral Countries through this Earth, where they may remember all the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152398:3"/> way, and all the ſeveral Steps and Stages of this Life, which the Lord God of all Creatures doth lead or carry them on theſe Fourty Years in the Wilderneſs, or theſe Thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcore Years and Ten, or Fourſcore Years, which is twice Fourty Years (for ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Days of Man are computed in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. and it holds ſtill thereabouts) in the Wilderneſs of this Earth, which is reckoned to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the middle part of the World. Where he hath made of one Blood all Nations of Men for to dwell on all the Face of the Earth, and hath determined the times before appointed, and the Bounds of their Habitation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Condition of Mankind, whilſt they are a little time Breathing on this Earth, is fitly compared to that of the <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aelites</hi> in the Wilderneſs on divers Reſpects: But particularly from that Deſcription which is given of it in <hi>Pſal. 107, 4, 5, 6, 7. They wandered in the Wilderneſs in a ſolitary Way, they found no City to dwell in, Hungry and Thirſty, their Souls fainted in them: Then they cried unto the Lord in their Trouble, and he delivered them out of their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes; and he led them forth by the Right Way, that they might go to a City of Habitation,</hi> Now here we have no continuing City, but Heaven is that City of Habitation, and this Earth is but a through fare unto it; as we now go through a little Town or Village unto a great City. This is now our preſent Condition on Earth, as we ſtand towards God. <hi>We wander in the Wilderneſs in a ſolitary Way.</hi> As we are meer Men abſtracted from the Aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Word and Spirit; Our Thoughts concerning God, are but Imaginations, Our Words are Miſtake or Falſhood, Our Actions are but Errors and Turnings aſide from the Right Way. This appears by thoſe Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, Pagans and Indians, who are the Workmanſhip of God as well as we; but for want of the Scriptures and the Light of the Goſpel, as to that Inviſible Being who made them, or as to that Inviſible World, they and we are all entring into, They <hi>Grope for the Wall like the Blind, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152398:3"/> they Grope as if they had no Eyes,</hi> Iſa. 59. 10. Even where is an appearance of the outward Worſhip of God and Chriſtianity, How many do wander in their Acts pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Religion? For even that of the Generality &amp; Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude is ſo defiled with the things which ſavour of Men, and comes ſo ſhort off that Religion which is to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Soul, that the ſmall Remnant is either forced to come out of it, and touch not the Unclean thing; or elſe ſee well to it that their Righteouſneſs do exceed the Righteouſneſs of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> that their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion do exceed the Religion of the World, as it is commonly Preached and Practiſed at this Day, that even his Elect Children and Servants do wander here in the Wilderneſs in a <hi>Solitary Way,</hi> being Deſtitute, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and Tormented, they are People by themſelves, as the uſual Phraſe is; which indeed agrees to that Character the Holy Ghoſt gives of them, <hi>Feed thy People with thy Rod, the Flock of thine Heritage which dwell Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily in the Wood, in the midſt of Carmel,</hi> Micah 7. 14. The People of God <hi>Dwell Solitarily;</hi> although they are in the midſt of Neighbours and Acquaintance, ſuch as they are. <hi>Hungry and Thirſty, their Souls fainted in them.</hi> This is as to God, and as to that good Satisfactory and Enduring Thing, which he hath Promiſed to the Sons of Men, which on this Earth is kept in Suſpence, and not actually, or at leaſt not fully given; but we are all along ſeeking and labouring after it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then they Cried unto the Lord in their Trouble, and he delivered them out of their Diſtreſſes.</hi> This Trouble and Diſtreſs, is that ſame <hi>Bondage of Corruption,</hi> and that <hi>Groaning</hi> and <hi>Travelling in Pain,</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 21, 22. Which the preſent State of the Creation is under. And we being a part of it, this ſhould be our Buſineſs all our Life long, to Cry unto the Lord, and to call upon the Name of the Lord, to be delivered and ſaved from it: And that amidſt all the Wandering of others,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152398:4"/> or of our ſelves, he would lead us forth through this Earth, by the Right Way (there is a great deal in that) and when God doth lead, be you ſure to follow, and take notice, ſo <hi>the Lord alone did lead him, and there was no ſtrange God with him,</hi> Deut. 32. 12. Neither Idolatry, nor Covetouſneſs, nor Senſuality, for theſe are kinds of Idolatry, nor no ſtrange Luſt, nor no Sin, for in the Judgment of our Creator, any Sin is a <hi>ſtrange God,</hi> or a ſtrange Thing which ſhould not be there, <hi>viz.</hi> in any of his Creatures. Take theſe two Directions along with you, and obſerve them, <hi>viz.</hi> to follow when he leads, and that the Lord alone may lead thee, that there be no ſtrange God with thee, and I will warrant my Life for yours, that he will lead you, and alſo bring you by the Right Way unto a City of Habitation; which is Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Habitation of his Holineſs (for the ſame Power that ſent us here, will tranſlate us up to that High and Lof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Place, if we ſhall be found meet and worthy, where we ſhall be no longer Travellers, Pilgrims, or Strangers; but in a proper and true Sence Fellow-Citizens and Inhabitants for ever to abide. <hi>He led them forth by the Right Way.</hi> As for my ſelf, in my Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neying and Travelling, I have miſtook the Way, but by enquiry and going forward, I always arrived at the place at laſt where I would be. It is the very ſame in our way to Heaven. People may, yea and they do often miſtake the Right Way; but if they will keep on in the <hi>Way of Holineſs</hi> (which the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean ſhall not paſs over,</hi> Iſa. 35. 8.) if they will ſeek out of the Book of the Lord, and Read in the ſure Word of Propheſie; if they will take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eed to the Day Dawn and the Day Star in their Hearts, and do according to the Light which that ſhews them. If they will confer Experiences with the Saints that are on the Earth <hi>(for they that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eared the Lord ſpake often <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e to another)</hi> But above all, if they will be ſure to be Travelling on, and in motion, and always making
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152398:4"/> towards it, though perhaps in Twenty Miles we may go half a Mile or more about; though in Sailing over the Sea of this Life, ſometimes we cannot go directly forwards, by reaſon of contrary Winds; yet we may Sail this way and that way to make towards it, and at laſt, <hi>God bringeth them to their deſired Haven,</hi> Pſal. 107. 30. We Read in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles of the <hi>Fair Haven,</hi> Put one Letter more in, and <hi>Haven</hi> ſpells <hi>Heaven,</hi> which indeed is the <hi>Fair Haven;</hi> for it is all Fair and Clear there, it being above all Winds and Storms. This is our deſired Haven, or the Haven where we would be.</p>
            <p>More need not to be ſaid to Paralel our Condition here on Earth for Threeſcore Years and Ten, or Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Years, with that of the Wilderneſs for Fourty Years. In the Text it is ſaid, To Humble thee. And this ſeems to be the very Reaſon of thoſe ſeveral ſeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and harſh Diſpenſations of his Providence, as in ſending upon us Afflictions, Poverty, Sickneſs, and ſuch like. As alſo why he made us thus, and placed us in ſuch <hi>vile Bodies,</hi> Phil. 3. 21. In the vulgar Latin, there for it is <hi>Corpus Humilitatis,</hi> which ſignifies the Body of our Humiliation; or ſuch a Body as God hath prepared, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and thought fit for this our preſent State of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation and Imperfection, <hi>To Humble us.</hi> We are as it were Men and Women in Carcaſes. And truly if we know our ſelves, and particularly our own outward Frame, there is all the reaſon in the World, as God in making us thus, and cloathing us with ſuch Garments of Fleſh, which are ſo courſe, if I may ſo expreſs it, filthy and weak and little, did it on purpoſe and deſign to Humble us: So we ſhould be indeed Humbled. For wherefore is Earth and Aſhes Proud? Conſider what were we whilſt in the Womb; from thence we were <hi>caſt out to the loathing of our Perſon in the Day that we</hi> were <hi>Born,</hi> Ezek. 16. 5. What are we now? A Breathing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152398:5"/> Cold of Clay? A ſink of Flegm and Excrements<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What ſhall we be? Meat for Worms, Ghaſtlineſs, ſtink and Corruption? Canſt thou throughly think upon this and not be Humbled? However to ſuch as will be O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, the Language of Truth ſpeaks on this wiſe, It is the Will of our Heavenly Father and Creator, that during this ſhort time we are in this Wilderneſs of the Earth, we ſhould be very Low, Trembling and Poor in Spirit. Even by thine own Frame and Conſtitution, <hi>He hath ſhewed thee O Man</hi> (from within thy ſelf) <hi>what is good, and what doth the Lord require of thee, to walk hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with thy God,</hi> Micah 6. 8. And ſee that thou comply with his Mind herein.</p>
            <p>The Text goes on to add, <hi>to prove thee,</hi> to <hi>know what is in thine Heart, whither thou wouldeſt keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or no.</hi> Here is the Principal Intent Specified; and under this is comprised the Reaſon of almoſt all his doings towards the Children of Men, from the Day he firſt Created them on the Earth, until the End of time. He proved our firſt Parents, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> to know what was in their Hearts, whither they would keep his Commandments or no; and they did not keep them. And ſo he did afterward, Prove <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> who did keep them according to the Covenant and Meaſure as he did accept of. <hi>For I know</hi> Abraham <hi>that he will command his Children and his Houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the Way of the Lord,</hi> Geſi. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9. And ſo it is of all the Deſcendants from <hi>Abraham</hi> ever ſince, ſome did keep his Commandments, and ſome did not. Beſides that conſtant and continued Proving them throughout their Life, God doth ſometimes Prove his Children in an extraordinary manner, as he did tempt <hi>Abraham</hi> to offer up his Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> which was a great Inſtance of his Faith, and whereby he did know that he F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ared God. Seeng thou haſt not witholden thy Son, thine only Son from me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even the Beſt and deareſt thing,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152398:5"/> and all that he had of that Nature. It is a Wonderful thing to Conſider how he doth Prove all the Generations and Perſons of Mankind, one after this manner, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after that, according to their different Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Condition of Life, to know what is in their Hearts, whither they will keep his Commandments or no. The whole Hiſtory of the Bible, and of all his Servants, and Reaſonable Creatures mentioned therein, are to this purpoſe. The Servants of God did keep his Commandments, but all his Creatures, whom he had endued with Reaſon, did not. And ſo it is of all the Men and Women that ever trod upon this Earth; whoſe Names, though they are not Recorded in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ook, yet they are in the Regiſter of him, <hi>Who bringeth out that gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Hoſt of his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Creation by number, and calleth them all by their Names.</hi> So likewiſe beſides the ordinary manner of dealing with his People, he did tempt and prove <hi>Job</hi> by his great and extraordinary Afflictions, who in all them Sinned not, nor yet Charged God fooliſhly; for indeed God did well and wiſely as to him. <hi>What is Man that thou ſhouldeſt Magnifie him, and that thou ſhouldſt ſet thine Heart upon him, and that thou ſhouldſt Viſit him every Morning, and try him every Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Job 7. 17, 18. All things are full of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, even to the neceſſary Victuals which we Eat, for there may be Gluttony; and to the Clothes which we wear, for there may be Pride; even to all our Thoughts (and we do think continually) for there may be, and too often is, Vanity and Evil. To our Words, for in the <hi>multitude of them, there wants not Sin;</hi> and we may ſoon Speak Falſhood or Folly; and ſo to our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Doings; for there Sin, Iniquity, and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion do beſet us round, and it is eaſy falling into any of them, And ſo all Companies and Converſation with our fellow Creatures do prove a Snare unto us, or there is Man Pleaſing and Perverting the thing that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152398:6"/> is Right, to humour and comply with thoſe that are above us in outward Degree or Riches. As alſo there is a fear of <hi>Bearing Witneſs unto the Truth,</hi> and Speaking it out, leaſt they ſhould fall under the Diſpleaſure of Men. Many ſuch like things do ſhew that the Trial of Man is had every Moment, as alſo it is had when he is at, and amidſt the Worſhip and Service of God, and at Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Duties.</p>
            <p>It is properly and truly a Life of Probation and Trial. And we are here upon, or according to our good or ill Behaviour, ſo we ſhall have the Eternal Favour of God, or be rejected by him. Like as Apprentices are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly put out a Month before hand for Trial, to ſee whither the maſter will take them for Seven Years or not, ſo theſe Seventy Years on this Earth, we Men and Women are upon Trial for all Eternity; God hereby Proving us, whither we ſhall be meet to be partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light, or Reprobates. <hi>Reprobate Silver ſhall Men call them, becauſe the Lord hath Rejected them,</hi> Jer. 6. 30. As it is with the Earth it ſelf, ſo it will be with the Men and Women, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Inhabitants thereof. <hi>For the Earth which drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Rain that cometh oft upon it, receiveth Bleſſing from God. But that which beareth Thornes and Briers, is Rejected, and is nigh unto Curſing, whoſe End is to be Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Heb. 6. 7. 8. The good Fiſhes are to be gathered into Veſſels, and the bad are to be caſt away. <hi>So ſhall it be at the End of the World. The Angels ſhall come forth and ſhall Sever the Wicked from among the Juſt.</hi> Mat. 13. 41, 42. So God will do at the End of World, but all this mean while, during which the Generations paſs through here, whither it be Six or Seven Thouſand Years, it is the time of their Probation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Trial, but after that is over, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, God will then proceed to a Deciſion and Sentence.</p>
            <p>For the more effectual Trial and Probation of Mankind, He hath alſo ordained a Life of Faith, and a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152398:6"/> State of Abſence from the Lord, which is Grounded from 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 6, 7. Whilſt we are at home in the Body, we are abſent from the Lord, for we Walk by Faith and not by Sight.</hi> The right Underſtanding of theſe two things, This Life of Trial and Probation, and this walking by Faith do clearly open unto us the Nature of God's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Dominion over us Men. It was never known in any Nation, Country and Language, that the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple there ſhould obey a King or Ruler, whom neither they themſelves, nor yet any of his Subjects ever ſaw: Which laſt it put in, becauſe whereas Earthly Kings do Rule over Countreys of vaſt Extent and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and of Millions of Inhabitants who are diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all over it; and he being but little and Circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in Paſſion as other Men, it ſeldom or never happens that he doth ſee all his Subjects, nor yet do all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ever ſee him. But yet a very great many do, and have ſeen him: So that all the others having them for undoubted Witneſſes and Aſſurance, that there is ſuch an One, they do, and muſt obey him, nevertheleſs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they have not ſeen him. But as to God, tho' he fills Heaven and Earth, and all things, and all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with his Preſence; though his Kingdom is an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom, and his Dominion endureth through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Generations; yet no Man of any Generation or Country did ever ſee him. <hi>No Man hath ſeen God at any time: The Only begotten Son, which is in the Boſom of the Father, he hath declared him,</hi> John 1. 18. And yet he reqires and expects to be obeyed by all Nations, Kindred and Languages, yea by all the Inhabitants of the World. Whom we are to Obey, though we do not ſee him, and all One as if we did ſee him. And though God gives no preſent Viſible Recompence, but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, We often ſuſtain outward Loſs, Inconvenience and Hardſhip for performing Service unto him, yet he Requires it. Hereby God is Glorified, and here is the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152398:7"/> Faith and Patience of the Saints to perform it neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. <hi>Now Faith is the Subſtance of things hoped for, and the Evidence of things not ſeen.</hi> And this Faith doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly terminate upon an Unſeen God, as it's Object. <hi>Whom having not ſeen ye Love, in whom, though ye ſee him not, yet believing, ye Rejoyce with</hi> Joy Unſpeakable and full of Glory. Receiving the End of your Faith, the Salvation of your Souls, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 8, 9. We Read very often in Scripture of the Name of the Lord, <hi>The Heathen ſhall fear the Name of the Lord, ſo declare the Name of the Lord in</hi> Zion, Pſal. 102. 15, 21. And of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Name of the Lord.</hi> Which Name of the Lord (to ſpeak after the manner of Men) doth ſuppoſe and import as much, as if his Perſon were diſtant, and not ſeen by us. But here to purſue the like Reaſoning, as is in <hi>Pſal. 75. 1. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee, O God do we give Thanks: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee do we give Thanks; for that thy Name is near, thy Wonderous Works declare.</hi> So here it is, Unto thee O God do we yield Obedience, and render Worſhip, for that thy Name, or rather thy Perſon included in that Name, is real thy Viſible Works declare, which we cannot ſo much as look upwards or downwards; or without doors, but we muſt ſee them. We may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with our outward Bodily Eyes, the Truth and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of what he hath affirmed, <hi>for I lift up my Hand to Heaven, and ſay, I Live for ever,</hi> Deut, 32. 40. For we do, or may continually ſee that vaſt fabrick of the Heavens and the Earth, and all therein contained, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by the Word of his Power, in a moſt Wonderful and Aſtoniſhing manner. That vaſt and wide Roof of the Firmament, or Sky is kept up by his Almighty and Viſible Hand, without any Viſible Beams or Pillars. By the way, the declaring of theſe things unto ye, is a proper and uſeful kind of Preaching, Becauſe it is a <hi>Publiſhing the Name of the Lord, Aſcribe ye grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſs unto our God,</hi> Deut. 32. 2. And a ſpeaking of the <hi>Wonderful
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152398:7"/> Works of God,</hi> Acts 2. 11. Which the Apoſtles did to their Hear-ers.</p>
            <p>It is a wonderful thing to Conſider how the God, who made all things, and filleth all things, ſhould yet be ſo little manifeſted unto Men; that he, who is all Brightneſs and Glory, ſhould not be ſeen amongſt us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he, who made and faſhioned us, in whom we live and move and have our being, ſhould be ſo little per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by us; that when he <hi>filleth Heaven and Earth with his Preſence,</hi> yet any ſhould Live without God in the World. Surely Darkneſs hath covered the Earth, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d groſs Darkneſs the People. The Sun gives Light upon it by Day, and the Moon by Night; and yet there is a greater Obſcurity round about, which the dull Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment perceives not. There is yet a worſe and greater Obſcurity in thoſe, who ſee and walk thereon. Strange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> That Hitherto it ſhould not be as yet Univerſally ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled as to all the Inhabitants of the Earth, <hi>At that Day ſhall a Man look to his Maker, and his Eyes ſhall have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 17. 7. Whom he might ſee with the Eyes of his U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>derſtanding being onlightened, as he doth with his outward Bodily Eyes behold the Works of God, and the Earth which he Treads on. By the Air he Breaths and moves in, he might have a Sence and Reſemblance of him that is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible. Who doth alſo beſet him behind and before, is with him in his going out, and coming in, and is acquainted with all his Ways. The leaſt conceiving and Inward Reaſoning, will Inſtantly lead unto the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of him, Lift up your Eyes on High, and behold who hath Created theſe things; for it muſt be ſome One who made all theſe things; for we do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, and know of the Houſes which we Inhabit, that ſome did Build them, although that was before we were Born. And this great Houſe of the World muſt needs have been framed by him, who <hi>Built all things; and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152398:8"/> that is God,</hi> Heb. 3. 4. <hi>Through Faith we underſtand that the Worlds were Framed by the Word of God; ſo that things which are ſeen, were not made of things which do app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> Heb. 11. 2. The Heavens continue ſtanding as they were from the Days of the Creation; yet that once was, and muſt needs have been. But then further, the very continuance and upholding of them doth plainly Demonſtrate, and Point out his Eternal Power and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</p>
            <p>Beſides the Ignorance, Sot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhneſs, and Negligence of Man in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and Seeking God,</hi> Pſal. 14. 2. Some Reaſon why he is not ſo Known, and Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Inhabitants of the Earth, is through his own Ordering, if I may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Speak; for I gather it from his own Word of Truth, <hi>Verily, thou art a God that hideſt thy ſelf, O God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>the Saviour,</hi> Iſa. 45. 15. If I may ſo expreſs it, tho' he is in them, and before them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet he doth hide <hi>himſelf,</hi> behind the Skreen of Created things. <hi>And it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame to paſs that in the Morning Wat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, the Lord looked unto the Hoſt of the Egyptians through the Pill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of Fire, and of the Cloud,</hi> Exod. 14. 24. And ſo he doth continually look unto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nhabitants of the Earth, through the material and viſible things, although we cannot ſee him, Becauſe he is Immaterial and Inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. God ſeeth us, when we do not ſee him. He ſeeth us always, but we do not ſee him at any time. <hi>Behold, I Go forward, but he is not there; and backward, but I cannot perceive him. On the left Hand where he doth work, but I cannot behold him. He hideth himſelf on the Right Hand</hi> (Mark that Phraſe, again of hiding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) <hi>that I cannot ſee him. But he knoweth the Way that</hi> I take (this again confirms what is aforeſaid, though we do not ſee God, yet God ſeeth us) <hi>when he hath tried me, I ſhall come forth as Gold,</hi> Job 23. 8, 9, 10. By an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexing which laſt here his Spirit by the Mouth of <hi>Job,</hi> doth Intimate and ſet forth, that God doth thus, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152398:8"/> to <hi>try Man.</hi> This ſame Truth and Obſervation is yet more clearly Expreſſed in <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 20. Which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo comes directly to the ſence of my Text, to Prove thee, to know what is in thine Heart, whither thou wilt keep his Commandments or no: Here God ſpeaks on this wiſe, <hi>I will hide my Face from them, I will ſee what their End ſhall be; for they are a very froward Generation, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in whom is no Faith.</hi> Now put all this together, and we are given to underſtand, that whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> God hideth himſelf, and hideth his Face, as he hath done ſince the Creation, hereby he doth Try and Prove the Children of Men, and knows what is in their Hearts, and ſees what their End will be. In <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. There is as it were a Hiſtory and Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earſal of all that Ignorance, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, Sottiſhneſs, Blindneſs, Folly, and Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Mankind towards their God; and the Reaſon of all is as it were ſummed up, and Rendred in the Twentieth Verſe, becauſe <hi>God hideth his Face,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>they are a froward Generation, Children in whom is no Faith.</hi> For had they but any Faith, they might find out God; notwithſtanding he is Inviſible, and he hideth himſelf, and he hideth his Face; and if they did but once find him out, and know him, it is impoſſible that ever Man, a Reaſonable Creature, ſhould carry himſelf thus perverſly and contrariwiſe towards God, as he hath done. Although the People of the World do reckon upon Sin, as a thing of Naught, of no Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy and of no Account, yet all Sin is againſt God. And I am perſuaded that (notwithſtanding it is ſo ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, common and cuſtomary in the World, as alas now it is) People would no more commit Sin againſt God, if they did ſee him with his Bow bent and his Sword drawn (the Scripture hath deſcribed him in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) ready to take Vengeance on them for the ſame, and if they did throughly know and believe how that there is a Juſt Recompence of Reward annexed to every
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152398:9"/> Tranſgreſſion and Diſobedience, than now they dare Curſe the King to his Face, for which they ſhould incur his ſevere Wrath and Diſpleaſure Immediately. But if God was as Viſible as our Governours after the Fleſh are, then there could be no ſuch thing as Faith at all, there could be no Trial of Obedience from the Heart (for it might be done only with outward Act) How could he then ſo effectually Prove us, to know what is in our Heart, whither we will keep his Commandments or no. Though God is not Viſible, yet his Works are: By the greatneſs and vaſtneſs, whereof we may very well Apprehend and Aſcribe greatneſs unto our God, for it muſt needs be a Great God who hath Created ſuch great things. So, although he is Inviſible, yet his exceeding Greatneſs ſhould make us more afraid; and keep us more in Subjection, then all viſible Terrors or Temptations, which are but little; as alſo his Eternal Promiſes and Threatnings ſhould weigh more with us, then all preſent things, which are but momentary and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dden.</p>
            <p>Here is the <hi>Revelation of the Myſtery which was kept ſecret ſince the World began, but now is made manifeſt, and by the Scriptures of the Prophets, according to the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Everlaſting God made known to all Nations for the Obedience of Faith,</hi> Rom. 16. 25, 26. This thing, an <hi>Obedience of Faith,</hi> to Obey God whom we have not ſeen, and to Obey for unſeen things; all which is Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by Faith, whoſe Object is an unſeen God, and unſeen Things. Though it is made known and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt enough by the Scriptures and by the Goſpel, and though it hath been Preached and Declared to the World, yet it is a <hi>Myſtery</hi> to them at this Day. But his Children and Servants, his Elect and Choſen One<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do underſtand as well what it is to Obey and Serve an unſeen God, for unſeen Things, as the Labourers in the Vineyard did, when they worked for a Peny a Day, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152398:9"/> as Servants and Labourers know for whom and or what they Labour, when they do work for their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> according to the Fleſh for Yearly Wages, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or ſo much a Day. An Obedience of Faith doth apre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend things Future, all one as things preſent; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith is the Subſtance of things hoped for. Now thing ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for, are not as yet. And though ſome may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> apt to Imagine that things not yet, are not Subſtanc, yet the Holy Ghoſt knew better, when he expreſſed it after that manner, then Scoffers and Unbelievers, who are apt to Object, and ſay on this wiſe. For I pray you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udge ye in your own Reaſon, is there not as much Subſtance in things diſtant as in things near? Is there not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame Subſtance in things to come, as in things preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? For even things preſent were once to come. Is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere not as much Subſtance in Heaven as in Earth? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> believe, that whoſoever ſhall be counted worthy to encer therein, he will find Ten Thouſand times more. But the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this World are Ignorant, and Puzzled at this Myſtery of an Obedience of Faith, becauſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Threatnings of God are future and to come, therefore People do not Regard nor Fear them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Faith would here receive and embrace thoſe Promiſes, and alſo be Overawed by the Threatnings; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they are future and Diſtant, all one as if they were preſent and ſenſible before them. But the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the World are a <hi>very froward Generation, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in whom is no Faith.</hi> There is little or no true Faith amongſt Men. And hereupon, <hi>Becauſe Sentence againſt an Evil Work is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the Hearts of the Sons of Men are fully ſet in them to do Evil,</hi> Eccleſ. 8. 11. There is a great deal in this. I had almoſt ſaid, that this is the Cauſe and Reaſon of all the Irreligion and Ungodlineſs, Sin a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Wickedneſs, that is abroad in the Earth, becauſe God doth not preſently Puniſh Men and Women for the ſame. It is this which makes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152398:10"/> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Armour-Proof and Hardned againſt the Miniſtry of is Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and our Denunciation of the Terrors of the ord againſt them. And ſo it is of that Evil People whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> refuſe to hear my Words, which walk in the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of their Hearts. <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. 10. For both ſorts think in the Hearts, although the Word &amp; the Miniſtry there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeak Evil and Miſery to us, yet nothing comes of it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or we are as Healthful in Body, as Proſperous in outwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Eſtate, and ſeem as Merry and contented in Mind as other People. The Tabernacles of Robbers Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and they that provoke God are ſecure into whoſe Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s God bringeth abundantly, <hi>Job 12. 6. Wherefore do the Wicked Live, become old, yea, mighty in Power. Their Seed is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtabliſhed in their ſight with them, and their Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring before their Eyes. Their Houſes are ſafe from Fear, neither is the Rod of God upon them, Their Bull Gendereth, and faileth not, their Cow Calveth, and Caſteth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Calf,</hi> Job 21. 7, 8, 9, 10. So their Ground bringeth forth Corn and Graſs, all one as that of other People. <hi>God is kind to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthankful and to the Evil,</hi> Luke 3. 37. <hi>For he maketh his Sun to riſe on the Evil and Good, and ſendeth Rain on the Juſt and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt,</hi> Mat. 6. 35. <hi>There is a Juſt Man that periſheth in his Righteouſneſs, and there is a Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man that prolongeth his Life in his Wickedneſs,</hi> Eccleſ. 7. 15. <hi>There be Juſt Men unto whom it happeneth according to the Work of the Wicked; again there be Wicked Men to whom it happeneth according to the Work of the Righteous,</hi> Eccleſ. 8. 14. <hi>No Man knoweth Love or Hatred</hi> (that is of God) <hi>by all that is before him. All things come alike to all. There is one event to the Righteous and the Wicked, to the Good, to the Clean and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean; to him that Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth, and to him that Sacrificeth not, as is the Good ſo is the Sinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, and he that Swear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, as he that Feareth an Oath,</hi> Eccleſ. 9. 1, 2. Though God hath been Pleaſed to ordain and ſuffer it ſo to be; yet it is before ſaid, that the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and the Wiſe, and their Works, are in the Hand of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152398:10"/> God.</hi> And ſo it follows by the ſame Conſequence of things, that the Works and Doings of Sinners and the Wicked, are in the memorial and Regiſter of God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for him to bring forth the ſame unto future Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and make a ſeveral Diſtribution thereupon. For <hi>ſince the Fathers fell aſleep, All things continue as they were ſince the beginning of the Creation,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 4. And ſo People are Born, Marry and Die Promiſcuouſly and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently without any odds between Righteous and Wicked, Godlineſs or Ungodlineſs, Obedience or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, of one Man between another. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do ſpeak fully and abundantly hereof in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and alſo they mention particularly in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. how the Sinners and Wicked, <hi>who walk after their own Luſts,</hi> do hereupon Sin yet more and more, and go on ſecurely, and without fear, becauſe of their preſent Proſperity and Impunity in this Life. Whereas I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Solemnly and Seriouſly as I ſee and obſerve theſe things, to me it is the greateſt Argument, Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and full Aſſurance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that all things are indeed ſo as they are ſpoken of in Scripture. And I do through this, which hath been a Cloud and Stumbling Block to ſome, ſee clearly and apprehend plainly the Nature of God's Kingdom and Dominion over Men, to be on this wiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> As <hi>about the time of Forty Years, he ſuffered the manners of the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>in the Wilderneſs,</hi> Acts 13. 18. ſaith our Text, <hi>To prove them.</hi> In like manner for about the time of Threeſcore Years and Ten, or Fourſcore Years, he doth ſuffer the manners of all the ſeveral Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Men and Women, of all Countreys in this Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of the Earth, letting them go on as they will, to <hi>ſee what they will do, and what their End will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> This is his Eternal Decree which ſeems to be Eſtabli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon great Wiſdom; for hereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e doth Effectua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y prove them, to know what is in their Heart, whither t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey will keep his Commandments or no. This very ſame Order
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152398:11"/> and Diſpenſation of the things of God towards us Men, may be underſtood from that of the Apoſtle, as indeed the whole Series &amp; Deſign of Scripture hath a Relation and Tendency to what he hath written, <hi>For we muſt all appear before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt, that every one may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive for the things done in the Body, according to that he hath done, whither it be good or bad,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 10. Whereby it is clearly ſhewn forth and intimated, that People do not receive in this Life according to the things that they have here done in the Body, but they will receive for them in the Day of Judgment, and in the ſucceeding E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. There will be nothing done of this, until theſe Bodies are laid in the Graves, and <hi>an Hour is coming after that, in the which all that are in their Graves ſhall hear his Voice, and ſhall come forth, they that have done good unto the Reſurrection of Life, and they that have done Evil, unto the Reſurrection of Damnation,</hi> John 5. 28, 29<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God will make one Work and Reckoning of it altogether, according to <hi>Mat. 25. 32. And before him ſhall be gathered all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And the Deſtruction of the Sinners and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors ſhall be together,</hi> Iſa. 1. 28. Even of all Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Countries, although now they Live out their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time, and Dye as other Men. The Spirit of God ſaith by the ſame <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> The <hi>Sinner being an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years Old, ſhall be accurſed,</hi> Iſa. 65. 20. The Word of God doth Speak Evil of him now, and Evil ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal him hereafter; although as yet he hath felt nothing of outward Harm or Evil. Good Men have been offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the preſent Proſperity and Impunity of the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. We hear frequently thereof in the Old Teſtament, but not altogether ſo much in the New. Thoſe who had chiefly Temporal Promiſes to encourage them to Obedience, might well Startle and Stumble, when the Diſobedient received the ſame in Effect. <hi>Verily I have cleanſed my Heart in vain,</hi> Pſal. 73. 13. There was not then ſo clear a Revelation of the Judgment to come,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152398:11"/> and of the ſucceeding Eternity, which is to make a wide Deciſion and vaſt Difference between the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and the Wicked. This would have inſtantly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied all their doubts. But now Chriſtians, who are aſſured of all this have no Reaſon to be Envious at the Fooliſh, when they ſee the Proſperity of the Wicked. Yet, Do ye think the Scripture ſaith in vain? <hi>The Spirit that dwelleth in us, luſteth to Envy,</hi> Jam. 4. 5. The difference between the Sins of the Regenerate and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate is, the Regenerate have little motions and tendencies towards the ſame Sins, which they cruſh and keep ſhort, but the others ſuffer them to break forth into op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Act. And ſo there are at this Day in ſincere good People, ſome little Inclinations or Luſtings to Envy. They are apt to be Grieved, that they who Provoke or Deſpiſe God, ſhould Flouriſh and ſeem outwardly in better Plight then themſelves. There is a carnal Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture, ſomething for themſelves, when they Cry out O Lord, How long ſhall the Wicked Triumph? How long wilt thou ſuffer them to do on this wiſe? Perhaps they have their Portion in this Life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. 14. As <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did obſerve, that was the Reaſon of the long Proſperity and Continuance of the Roman Empire, for their Exerciſe of Moral Vertues. Like, as we Read in One of the Prophets, <hi>That God did give</hi> Egypt <hi>to</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar <hi>for Wages,</hi> in ſerving him with his Army in ſuch a Work as he would have done. And this ſame is the very Reaſon why many People have Health and Proſperity, Riches and long Life, who will yet never go to Heaven; but they are Rewarded here for that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle good they have done. And therefore the Pſalmiſt Prays by the Spirit, <hi>Deliver my Soul from Men, which are thy Hand O Lord, from Men of the World, which have their Portion in this Life, and whoſe Belly thou filleſt with thy hid Treaſure.</hi> They are full of Children, and leave the reſt of their Subſtance to their Babes. This would not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152398:12"/> content and ſatisfy him, but he was rather afraid of it. As for me (By which kind of Speech he would Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and Exempt himſelf from them) I will behold thy Face in Righteouſneſs, I ſhall be ſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied when I awake in thy Likeneſs. I have Read of a certain Godly Man, who when he was Exalted to great Perfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues, he did very much fear, leaſt thereby God meant to give him his Portion in this Life; and thereupon he was doubtful whither he ſhould accept of it, yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he did. However we are to let God alone with the Ways of his Providence; for he, and not we poor Wretches, knoweth what he hath to do. How he deals with others, what is that to us? We may reſt fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and moſt certainly aſſured with what the Wiſe Man ſaith, <hi>Though a Sinner do Evil an Hundred times and his Days be Prolonged, yet ſurely I know it ſhall be well with them which Fear God, which Fear before him,</hi> Eccleſ. 8. 12. God cannot be Unrighteous; and if he deals more Bountifully with the Wicked in this Life then with you, certainly you will fare better then they in that Life which is to come. It will be better for thoſe who in the Days of their Fleſh, Lived before him in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs, then with thoſe who in the ſame Days of their Fleſh did Deſpiſe God, or Lived in ſome Tranſgreſſion or Diſobedience the ſame while. Shall not the Judge of all the Earth do Right? Yea, He ſhall do Right, and make an exact Diſtribution <hi>(Judgment will I lay to the Line, and Righteouſneſs to the Plummet)</hi> to every Man according as his Work hath been. Doth any wiſe or knowing Man envy Oxen or Sheep as he ſees them Feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in good Paſtures, but he rather Pities the poor Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures, becauſe he apprehends what it is for, to Fat them for the Shambl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. This is the very caſe as to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of the Wicked or Sinners, <hi>Righteous art thou O Lord when I plead with thee, yet let me Talk with thee of thy Judgments. Wherefore doth the Way of the Wicked Proſper?
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152398:12"/> Wherefore are all they happy that deal very Treachero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, thou haſt planted them. Yea, they have taken Root, they grow, yea, they bring forth Fruit. Thou art near in their Mouth</hi> (and ſo they were outward Worſhippers, and did talk of God in a general Way) <hi>and far from their Reins. But thou O Lord knoweſt me, thou haſt ſeen and tried my Heart towards thee</hi> (whereby the Prophet doth import his own ſincere Service towards God, and yet it was not outwardly ſo well with him: But he goes on to add,) <hi>Pluck them out like Sheep for the Slaughter, and prepare them for the Day of Slaughter,</hi> Jer. 12. 1, 2, 3. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſo the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith by the Spirit unto the Rich Men, <hi>Ye have Lived in Pleaſure on the Earth, and been Wanton, and Nouriſhed your Hearts as in the Day of Slaughter,</hi> Jam. 5. 5. Tremble at this ye Gentry and Senſualiſts, and Merry Men of this preſent Age and Generation. Though thoſe Bruitiſh Men know it not, neither doth a Fool underſtand this, What? It follows, <hi>When the Wicked ſpring at the Graſs, and when all the Workers of Iniquity do Flouriſh, it is</hi> (there it is Pointed out) <hi>that they ſhall be deſtroyed for ever,</hi> Pſal. 92. 6, 7. So it will be for ever at laſt, although they are not preſently deſtroyed at the very ſame time when they commit their Wickedneſs and Iniquity. Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lek <hi>was the firſt of the Nations, but his latter End ſhall be, that he periſh for ever,</hi> Num. 24. 20. The Decree and Purpoſe of God ſtands on this wiſe, <hi>For the Lord God of Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences ſhall ſurely Requite,</hi> Jer. 51. 56. At the time Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, when they come Dye, and after that the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>As by a Right Underſtanding of the Nature of God's Kingdom and Dominion over us Men, we come to know the very Reaſon why he doth not preſently Puniſh Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but oftentimes ſuffers them to Proſper. So by the ſame Reaſon of things we may learn, wherefore he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers or inflicts Afflictions and Calamities on Godly and Righteous People. It is hard and ſomirk to think in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152398:13"/> ones Mind, Verily <hi>I have cleanſed my Heart in vain, and waſhed my Hands in Innocency; for all the Day long have I been Plagued, and Chaſtned every Morning,</hi> Pſal. 73. 13, 14. That when Man ſerves God diligently and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and leads an upright and innocent Life, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n he ſhould meet with greater and ſorer Troubles. To think this is Painful to One. Our Nature is Impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent thereat and Reſents it hardly. But this was the Lot of the Generation of thy Children in former Days; and therefore we are not to think that any ſtrange or new thing, hath happened unto us. <hi>But call to Remembrance the former Days in which after ye were Illuminated, ye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured a great fight of Afflictions, Partly, whilſt ye were made a gazing Stock, both by Reproaches and Afflictions; and whilst ye became Companions of them that were ſo uſed,</hi> Heb. 10. 32, 33. The Apoſtle writes this to thoſe precious and beſt Saints and Servants of God which were in that Day. And I know a Man who hath had a good Mind towards God from his tender Years, who hath made it his buſineſs and conſtant endeavour to keep, and alſo to do the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments from his Youth up; who when he hath been Perſecuted in Body, and been oppreſſed and rendred Poor in his outward Eſtate, It hath been Tauntingly and Sarcaſtically ſaid unto him, Is this all that your Prayers, Religion, and Faſting hath come unto? The Scoffer did go on to add, If I were to be Religious, I would be Religious for ſomewhat, and not thereby to be Rendred Miſerable (which might indeed be done in their meaning by cloſe Methods of Hypocriſy, but not by continuing whole and ſtedfaſt in God's Covenant, without Tranſgreſſion of, or Variation from ſome part of his written Word, conſidering how the World hath been, and is) but they who talk after this manner, have not Faith, and they know not what it is to Live by Faith, or to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ender an Obedience of Faith. We Read ſomewhat like hereof in the Book of the Lord. <hi>Many
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152398:13"/> there be which ſay of my Soul, There is no help for him in God,</hi> Selah. Pſal. 3. 2. <hi>My Tears have been my Meat Day and Night, while they Continually ſay unto me, Where is thy God? When I remember th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe things, I pour out my Soul in me, as with a Sword in mine Bones, mine Enemies Reproach me, while they ſay Daily unto me, Where is thy God?</hi> Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 42. 2, 3, 10. <hi>I Remembred God, and was Troubled, I Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, and my Spirit was Overwhelmed,</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lah. <hi>I have conſidered the Days of Old, the Years of Ancient Times, I Call to Remembrance my Song in the Night, I Commune with mine own Heart, and my Spirit made diligent ſearch,</hi> Pſal. 77. 3. Yea, I have ſometimes obſerved, that when I have walked with God yet more cloſely, and have wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon him more diligently, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing conſcious of no Sin or Fault, yet a greater Affliction or Vexation hath enſued immediately thereupon. Truly this was a very ſore Trial, that when one ſhould more expect and hope for Good from the Hands of God, then to meet with Evil. Yea, An horrible Thought and Temptation hath hereupon aroſe in my Mind (which indeed hath had that Effect, as to make me abate and diminiſh ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what from my former Zeal and Fervency, like unto that Saying of him, Behold, <hi>This Evil is of the Lord, What ſhould I wait for the Lord any longer,</hi> 2 Kings 6. 33. If only this comes of my Serving of God, ſhall I deſiſt and leave it off, and betake my ſelf to the like U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>godly Careleſs Life, or Formal Outſide Religion, which others do of my Circumſtances, Condition and Years. God for bid, I abhor the thoughts of it from the bottom of my Heart. But I will rather on the contrary make the true and right Inference, That Evil, Oppoſition and Trouble came from Satan the Adverſary (which God did ſuffer and overrule) to prove and try me yet more (wherefore I will yet more Reſiſt Satan, and act yet greater Revenge upon him) for there is a good ſort of <hi>Revenge</hi> mentioned in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 11. To the overthrow
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152398:14"/> of his Kingdom, hoth in my ſelf and others. Hitherto I have ſerved the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> a little, but now I will ſerve him much, and cleave yet more cloſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly unto him, for this Trouble and Affliction which hath befaln me. I will hear the Rod, and who hath appointed it. <hi>Come and let us</hi> (yet more) <hi>Return unto the Lord, for he hath broken, and he will heal us; he hath ſmitten, and he will bind us up. After two Days will he revive us, in the third Day he will raiſe us up, and we ſhall Live in his Sight. Then ſhall we know if we follow on to know the Lord.</hi> Hoſ. 6. 1, 2, 3. We may ſee and know more of God through the Dark Cloud of Afflictions and Troubles: As alſo then ſhall we know, if we follow on, to know the Lord, in the various Diſpenſations of his Providence, and in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral kinds of Trial, Temtation and Exerciſes, which he ordains or ſuffers to fall on us. And here it is, and ſhould be, that as we keep on Travelling, whither the Way under our Feet be Dry and Good, or Wet and Dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, through Thick and Thin, as we commonly ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As the Sailer ſtill makes towards the Haven, he is bound unto, come Fair Weather or Foul, gentle Gales, or <hi>Euroclyd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi> which ſignifies Tempeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uous Winds: So here is the Faith and Patience of the Saints, that the Righteous ſhould hold on his Way, and he that hath clean Hands, be ſtronger and ſtronger. For God and Heaven I am bent, bound and reſolved, this is my Journeys End, and here is my Deſired Haven, or the Haven where I would be. And I hope that by his Grace, and Strengthening me with Strength in my Soul (which I always ask in Prayer) for I am come to that Stedfaſtneſs and Purpoſe of Mind herein, that you may ſooner turn a Dromedary in his Courſe, then turn me aſide from going on ſtill in that way towards God, and the Habitation of his Holineſs, which he hath Chalked out in his Word, and ſhewed me in my Mind (what I ſpeak of my ſelf, when I Declare my own Experiences,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152398:14"/> I would that ye apply it to your ſelves alſo, for we are Fellow-Servants and Fellow-Travellers) through Good and Evil Report, through Shame and Diſhonour, as deceivers and yet true, in Afflictions, in Neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ies, in Diſtreſſes, through Plenty and Poverty, in Sickneſs and Health, in Proſperity and Adverſity, ſometimes at Liberty, and again through Priſons, Up-hill and Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, and ſometimes in a Plain, as our Way lie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. To have now, and then a ſmooth Voyage, and then to be toſſed to and fro. Even according to that Degree or Meaſure of Tribulation, which our Heavenly Father hath Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and Ordained we ſhall paſs through, before we come unto, and enter into his Kingdom. So that whereas I before mentioned, that thoſe Troubles and Afflictions its coming on me immediately after my cloſe walking with waiting on the Lord did ſeveral times heretofore make me abate &amp; diminiſh from my former Zeal and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, This was my Ignorance and Infirmity then. For now I perceive when I Underſtand things more, and aright, they ſhould rather have encreaſed and heightned and confirmed it ſo much the more. For hereby then Satan did get an Advantage over me, but if I had ſo done, as I now ſee that I ſhould have done, then I ſhould not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have made his own Devices of none Effect, but have turned and made them fall back upon himſelf. For this is the beſt way to deal with an Enemy, to turn his own Canon upon himſelf; and not only to ſpoil the Mines, but to ſpring thoſe Mines upon themſelves, which they had lain to Blow us up; or according to the Scripture Phraſe herein, that themſelves may fall into the Pit which they had digged for others. As it is written, <hi>Thou haſt ſhewed thy People hard things, thou haſt given us to drink the Wine of Aſtoniſhment.</hi> So <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad hard thoughts of God, when he ſaid, <hi>Wilt thou be unto me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as a Liar, and as Waters that fail?</hi> Jer. 15. 18. So I ſpeak it to my ſhame, and as a warning and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152398:15"/> to others, I have had hard thoughts of God, that whereas he had revealed himſelf to be good to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even to ſuch as are of a clean Heart, that even when I was by his Grace upon making my Heart clean then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Croſſes and Diſappointments, which our Fretful and Impatient Nature calls Evils, then was fulfilled, But as for me, <hi>my Feet were almoſt gone, my Steps had well nigh ſlipt, even</hi> to have turned a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de utterly from the Way of the Lord, or to have fallen down and go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therein. And truly unleſs it had been for ſome forcible Conſiderations drawn from the near Approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Death, and the ſucceeding Judgment which God put into my Mind, and they did weigh down, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule to continue ſtill in his Service (Bleſſed b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Name for it) I believe, and am afraid, that I had been an utter Apoſtate from the Ways of God.</p>
            <p>Moreover that the Heart be without Knowledge it is not Good, ſaid <hi>Solomon.</hi> But from hence we may ſee that Exceeding Advantage and Benefit of a full and through Knowledge concerning the things of God. It is all in all and the turning Point whereon doth depend the Eternal Salvation or Condemnation of Mankind. For where any one is ſaved, it is by Grace and Faith (both which do include within themſelves a Knowledge of the unſeen things of God) that they are ſaved. And ſo it is on the other Hand, <hi>My People are deſtroyed for lack of Knowledge,</hi> Hoſ. 4. 6. Which will be found true as to thoſe Miſerable Souls at the laſt Day, <hi>who ſhall be Puniſhed with Everlaſting Deſtruction from the Preſence of the Lord, and from the Glory of his Power,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1. 9. For had they known more of the things of God (and it was their own Fault and Negligence that they did not) they had eſcaped and never came to that State of final Condemnation and Perdition.</p>
            <p>The Conſideration hereof is an Unanſwerable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, why we ſhould do according to the Counſel and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152398:15"/> Direction of <hi>Solomon, A Wiſe Man will hear, and will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Learning,</hi> Prov. 1. 5. And for that End we ſhould take and lay hold on all Opportunities for Hearing the Word, and not be Ignorantly Confined to a dead and dull Miniſtry, or be blindly given up to follow a Blind Guide, and none elſe: But in the <hi>Multitude of Counſellors there is Safety,</hi> both in Temporal and alſo in Eternal Concerns.</p>
            <p>This Truth and Obſervation I make known, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea declare unto ye in the General, that ye may juſt perceive of what exceeding Uſe and Benefit and Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation it is to know <hi>fully</hi> and <hi>throughly</hi> (By both which Adverbs I difference it from that Knowledge in Part or by Halves, which is but a little coming forth out of Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and People ſhould never ſit down with a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in part, or at halves) the Nature of God's Kingdom and Dominion over Men, particularly in that Branch thereof, which relates to the <hi>Proſperity of the Wicked,</hi> or the <hi>Afflictions of the Righteous.</hi> For this hath been a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Stumbling Block, which hath hitherto hindred many People from coming into the Way of the Lord, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from walking on and continuing therein. This alſo hath a mighty Influence over the Minds of Men, in as much as it is Senſible and Viſible. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> cautions thoſe he writes unto, <hi>That they be not ſoon Moved or Shaken in Mind at the Afflictions which hath befaln him;</hi> knowing that thereunto we were appointed. And it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo contrary unto the Natural Prudence and Wiſdom of Men, to undertake or eſpouſe a broken Cauſe, or to embarke ones ſelf in a Shipwrackt Veſſel, hereupon it was that Chriſt Crucified, was to the Greeks Fooliſhneſs (as his Meanneſs and Condeſcention therein, was to the Jews a Sumbling Block, inaſmuch as they ſuppoſed that the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſias would be outwardly Glorious and Victorious over all his Enemies) for the Greeks could not think it Conſiſtent with their Vain Philoſophy, or Moral Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to receive and be <hi>partakers of the Afflictions of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:152398:16"/> And ſo far indeed it is true, that conſider it meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a Man within the Limits of this preſent Life &amp; ſhort Time, this Wiſdom will never be juſtified by her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. But let Faith come in, the Subſtance of things hoped for, which are to come, and the Evidence of things not ſeen; and this will quickly weigh down the Scale, and determine it, and carry it for the Knowledge of God and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Thus much is Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally Received and Acknowledged in this Chriſtian Nation and Country of our Nativity and Habitation. But ſtill there is that mixture of Unbelief, and ſo much which ſavours of Men, and of the Worldly and Fleſhly Nature, that it cannot throughly reliſh and digeſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions in the Ways of God, nor yet have they that Knowledge of the Moſt High, as to perceive his Favour and Loving Kindneſs therein, which is certainly true. <hi>For whom the Lord loveth, he Chaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth, according to what the Spirit ſaith, As many as I love, I Rebuke and Chaſten,</hi> Rev. 3. 19. Many are apt to doubt of the Favour of God, or to think they are not in the right way of his Worſhip (I have heard of Examples of this kind) becauſe of thoſe great continued Afflictions and outward Croſſes they meet with in the World. But herein all theſe People do err, not knowing the Scriptures nor the Power of God, nor the Way of the Diſpenſation of his Kingdom to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us Men. For the Reaſon and End of theſe Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are to prove and try them yet more, what is in their Heart, as Gold is tried in the Fire, and they are deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to draw us nearer and cloſer to God, as alſo to wean us the more from this preſent World. As it was noted before concerning the Proſperity of the Wicked, that they had their Portion in this Life, God intending there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to Reward them here for that little Good they had done, for none is ſo bad, but doth ſome little good or other. So it is here on the other Hand, there is a <hi>ſpot even of God's Children,</hi> Deut. 32. 5. And there was hardly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152398:16"/> any one ſo Righteous upon Earth (Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous excepted) who did not in ſome little thing or other put forth their Hand to Iniquity. They commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or Conſented to Iniquity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs or more; but they did not make a Trade or Continuance of it. For this cauſe <hi>they are here Chaſtened of the Lord, that they ſhould not be Condemned with the World,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 30, 31. Then it is that People do err, when they do not know the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For in theſe Scriptures very much is ſaid concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Proſperity of the Wicked, and the Afflictions of the Righteous. So much whereof hath been here decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and alledged out from thence, that the Reader may Judge and Underſtand in like manner of all the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. As the ſeveral things concerning it do ariſe up in his Thoughts, or as they find from their own Experiences, as alſo from the Obſervation they make from their own ſelves, as alſo from others abroad in the World, <hi>Seek ye out of the Book of the Lord and Read;</hi> for there a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Reaſon of the things of God may be had and underſtood. To know a thing as it ought to to be known, is to know it by its Conſequences and with the Reaſons thereof.</p>
            <p>Now of the things which we have ſpoken, this is the Sum. We have heard of the Nature of God's Kingdom and Dominion over Men, as the ſame is to prove a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d try them, to know what is in their Heart, and in order thereto, Secondly, God hath Eſtabliſhed for all Nations an <hi>Obedience of Faith.</hi> And Thirdly, All things happen alike to all, and alſo as a conſequent from the Firſt, he hath ſuffered the Proſperity of the Wicked, and to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the latter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et more, he hath ordained Troubles and Afflictions for the Righteous. All theſe ſeveral Heads of Diſcourſe do hang and depend one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as they are indeed and in reality linked on and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected together in the great Order and Concatenation of the things of God.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:152398:17"/>
            <p>It now remains to ſhew how the right Underſtanding of the Nature of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d's Kingdom and Dominion over Men, as it ſtands in this Order, and on this Wiſe, is a neceſſary h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lp towards the making a Continuing and Perſevering Work of it.</p>
            <p>Sin and Ungodlineſs do certainly hinder from making a Continuing and Perſevering Work of it, they being quite oppoſite and contrary thereunto, as Tranſgreſſion is contrary to Obedience, and the Service of God is Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ametrically Oppoſite, and Perfectly Contrary to no Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice at all. And therefore in order to make a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and perſevering Work of it, we muſt Sin not, and deny all Ungodlineſs. The Principal I had almoſt ſaid, only Reaſons why all the froward Inhabitants of the Earth do Sin againſt God, are theſe three. <hi>1ſt,</hi> Becauſe God doth not Render preſent Puniſhment. <hi>2dly,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God is out of ſight. And <hi>3dly,</hi> Becauſe God holds his Tongue, or keeps Silence. Now (obſerve this) a Right Underſtanding of the Nature of God's Kingdom and Dominion over us Men, as before Explained, doth anſwer all theſe and the like Imaginations in the Hearts of the Children of Diſobedience, or the Ignorant Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. For the ſame Word of Truth which ſaith, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Sentence againſt an Evil Work is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the Hearts of the Sons of Men are fully ſet in them to do Evil; elſewhere ſpeaks on this wiſe, <hi>I will Puniſh the World for their Evil, and the Wicked for their Iniquity,</hi> Iſa. 13. 11. The Puniſhment of God is almoſt throughout the whole Scripture, ſpoken of in the future Sence, he will or ſhall Puniſh. I do hereby tell and warn the Sinners and Tranſgreſſors and Hypocrites of this my Generation, who bleſs themſelves in their Heart, ſaying, They ſhall have Peace and Safety, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they walk in the Imagination of their Heart, to add one Sin to another. Who are apt to fancy as if God could not, or would not Puniſh, Becauſe he doth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152398:17"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot Puniſh them preſently, nor ſtrike them dead in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins. Hear ye this Word and Tremble, it is as eaſy for God to Puniſh them, or any of us, as for we to cruſh a Moth or kill the leaſt Fly or Inſect. For he taketh away our Breath, and we Dye, &amp; then the ſentence which was not before ſpeedily executed upon evil doers, doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be executed upon them. There is no need to pour down<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Judgments outwardly upon the Sinners Head, as he did upon the Cities of the Plain; for he can ſtir up a Diſeaſe fron within, which ſhall fetch out the Soul to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive for its Sinful &amp; Evil Deeds. Saith one, <hi>It is eaſy for the Lord to recompence a Man according to his ways in the day of his Death.</hi> Nay, He doth it not ſo properly in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct and particular day of Ones Death, as afterwards: for as when we begin an Action or Commence a Suit at Law againſt any Man, we do firſt Arreſt him by ſuch a Bayli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or Inferiour Officer, So God hath his Sergeant or Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger who ſits upon a Pale Horſe, whoſe Name is <hi>Death,</hi> and enters into Palaces all One as common Houſes (for no Place or Perſon is Priviledged againſt him) who ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts ſeverally all the Men and Women of all Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Countries, and fetches out their <hi>Souls from their Bodies,</hi> Luke 12. 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And then God begins his Proceſs or Proceedings againſt them, according to what they have done in this Life, whither Good or Evil. God could have Puniſhed Man in this Life and on this Earth, If he had ſo pleaſed. But his general Decr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is to ſpare them here, expecting that his Goodneſs, Forbearance and Long Suffering ſhould lead them to Repentance; but when he hath given them a ſpace to Repent, and they Repented not, then comes Retribution and Puniſhment. In this Life man doth Deſpiſe and Provoke the Lord God, but by Death God takes Vengeance on Man. <hi>For the Wrath of God is Revealed from Heaven againſt all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs of Men,</hi> Rom. 1. 18. Mark here diligently how it is expreſſed, It is <hi>Revealed,</hi> that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152398:18"/> is as much as to ſay, It is made known from Heaven; but it is not yet executed and ſenſibly felt, which will then be after the Breath of Men is gone out of their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, and their Souls are departed from their Bodies; or rather when they come to riſe up, and be Reunited a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, then they ſhall receive according to what they did in them in this Life and on this Earth. On this wiſe all the great Promiſes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Threatnings of God do ſtand: The Promiſes are now revealed or made known from Heaven, they belonging unto Godlineſs and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but are not yet Actually given. But they ſhall be certainly given in the appointed time, or rather at the End of time. And ſo the Threatnings are <hi>Revealed</hi> or made known from Heaven againſt all Ungodlineſs and Unrighteouſneſs of Men (by which laſt Word is ſignified all that is contrary unto that great and compleat Rule of Righteouſneſs in Scripture, Comprehending all our Duty to God as well as to our Neighbour; and not only In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and Wrong between Man and Man, although this is included alſo, it being contrary to that great and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Rule of Righteouſneſs therein mentioned) but God doth not execute his Threatnings preſently, nor yet are they ſenſibly felt by the Children of Men. Which yet ſome of them will ſenſibly feel, Smart and Groan under, after that their Spirits are deceaſed or departed from theſe Bodies of Clay, and are removed to another place then this Earth. God hath another place beſides this Earth, and another time beſides this Life, to fulfil and make good every thing to the leaſt little that he hath now ſpoken unto the Inhabitants of this Earth, in his written and Revealed Word.</p>
            <p>The Bruitiſh Man and Unbeliever, and Ignorant Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are apt to put off all this with a tranſient Jeſt, or their way of Proverb, What, Shall I ſpeak of it after I am Dead? Shall I feel Puniſhment when my Body can feel nothing, Implying as if there was an Impoſſibility
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152398:18"/> in this. No ſuch matter. Behold I ſhew you a Myſtery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Neither they, nor we ſhall Dye; but we ſhall be all changed. How now? What doſt thou contradict Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the Experience of all Mankind? It is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Men once to Dye. Notwithſtanding that I will however make out what I before ſaid and affirmed, that neither we nor yet Unbelievers ſhall ever Dye. We, that is our ſelves, our Souls ſhall not Dye. This is moſt true. For it is only the Body that Dies, then ſhall the Duſt return to the Earth as it was, and the Spirit to God who gave it. Then the Soul doth only deceaſe or depart from this Earthly Houſe God knows where. Hence Death is properly called a Deceaſe or Departure. Our Life is <hi>only taken off from the Earth,</hi> Acts 8. 33. but continued elſewhere<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſo the Soul is equally alive the next Hour or Day after her departure from the Body, all one as ſhe was when ſhe was in it. And it returns to God who gave it. And then ſhe hath a more Lively Hope or Comfortable Aſſurance of good things from him, or a Fearful Expectation of Evil things, according as ſhe hath behaved he ſelf well or ill in the Body.</p>
            <p>The ſhewing unto ye this Myſtery doth alſo anſwer thoſe two other Imaginations in the Children of Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, which emboldens them to Sin or Tranſgreſs againſt him, becauſe he is out of ſight and he now keeps Silence. For beſides, that the ſame Word of Truth which ſaith, <hi>No Man hath ſeen God at any time,</hi> Joh. 1. 18. doth elſewhere acquaint us with the <hi>Glorious Appearing of the Great God,</hi> Tit. 2. 13. And how that it ſhall be one day ſaid <hi>to the Cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>Behold your God,</hi> Iſa. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>9. The ſame Word, which doth take notice, how that God <hi>hath a long time refrained himſelf, and held his Peace, even of Old,</hi> Iſa. 57. 11. There it is added, <hi>And thou feareſt me not,.</hi> Even for that ſame Reaſon, <hi>becauſe he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld his Peace.</hi> And ſo he <hi>holdeth his Tongue when the Wicked De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth the Man that is more Righteous then he,</hi> Hab. 1. 13.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152398:19"/> And alſo whilſt that Evil, Iniquity and Treachery are Tranſacted, which is mentioned in the very ſame Verſe. And ſo it is whilſt the whole courſe of Sin and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion goes on as the ſame is committed by the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Mankind. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe things haſt thou done and I kept Silence,</hi> Pſal. 50. 21. Why here the ſame Word that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes how God <hi>holds his Peace, holds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Tongue, and keeps Silence,</hi> doth alſo mention and aſſure us, <hi>Our God ſhall come and ſhall not keep Silence. I will Reprove thee and ſet them in order before thine Eyes,</hi> Pſal. 50 3. 21. Even all the things that were done in this Life, and on this Earth. Behold, how one Scripture anſwereth to another, for it is even ſo in the Order and Determination of God. And we ſhall ſee it accordingly ſo fulfilled as it is written in the Scriptures, when the Lord God of <hi>Elijah</hi> ſhall take away all the Generations of Mankind from this Earth, and ſhall cauſe the Dead to ariſe, and the great Day of his Judgment is come and the after State.</p>
            <p>It was before mentioned, that though God is now out of ſight, yet at this very time he hideth himſelf, and ſtandeth behind the Skreen of his Viſible Creatures; yet Faith would find him out and perceive him for all that. As alſo an <hi>Obedience of Faith</hi> would approve our ſelves unto, and pleaſe him, all One as ever any Son or Servant did ſerve his Father or Maſter according to the Fleſh, whom he ſaw every day, and was almoſt continually with him. <hi>An Obedience of Faith</hi> muſt needs be accepted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſuch an Obedience as God himſelf hath Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and Eſtabliſhed; and the reaſonable Creature in this State cannot render any other. But I do believe and conceive, that as it is written, <hi>The Lord will come down in the ſight of all the People upon Mount</hi> Sinah, Exod. 19. 11. And it is af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erwards ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>, <hi>And Mount</hi> Sinah <hi>was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on a Smoke, becauſe the Lord deſcended upon it in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ire. And the Lord came down upon Mount</hi> Sinah <hi>on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op of the Mount,</hi> V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r. 18 20. Which Lord in <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 38. is ſaid
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152398:19"/> to be the Angel, Suppoſed to be the Son of God, even Jeſus Chriſt. We Read there, Verſe 16. and <hi>Exod. 20. 18, 19. Heb.</hi> 12. 21. What effect it had upon <hi>Moſes</hi> and upon all the People, as to caſt a very great Awe, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and Trembling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon them. The like is not to be expected again in this World. But this I do believe and conceive, that when the Inhabitants of the Earth of all Generations and Countreys from the Creation of the World unto the End thereof, ſhall be Summoned to meet with God by Death and Judgment at the laſt Trump, <hi>For the Trumpet ſhall Sound,</hi> then they ſhall have a ſenſible and more laſting Apprehenſion of the Great and Infinite God himſelf in Perſon, then the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had for the time of his Angel on Mount <hi>Sinah.</hi> For that particular Place, the whole Mount Quaked greatly, but then the Heavens and the Earth and the whole Creation will quake and be diſſolved to be changed and Created a new. This alſo I do apprehend and conceive that in the mean while after the ſeveral reſpective Deaths of particular Perſons until this great Day, as it is written, <hi>The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils Believe, and Tremble.</hi> So the Souls of ſuch Men and Women who in the Days of their Fleſh were Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and Provoking to God, will alſo Believe and Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Yea, they will be <hi>Magor Miſſabib, Fear round about,</hi> Jer. 20. 3. Becauſe that in the Inviſible World they will have nothing to harden themſelves, or to forget the ſence of their approaching Condemnation and Miſery, as now they have, as alſo, becauſe they will be nearer unto, and know more of God unto whom all Fleſh ſhall come.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. makes the Uſe and Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all this to our Hand, for he ſpeaking there of the very ſame admoniſhes, <hi>Seeing then that all theſe things ſhall be diſſolved, what manner of Perſons ought ye to be in all Holy Converſation and Godlineſs. Wherefore, Beloved, ſeeing that ye look for ſuch things, be diligent that ye may be found of him in Peace, without Spot and Blameleſs.</hi> Seeing that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152398:20"/> of the Kingdom and Dominion of God over Men ſtands on this wiſe, What can be a more forcible Motive and Perſuaſion then the Knowledge and Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration hereof for ye <hi>to be ſtedfaſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmoveable, always a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in the work of the Lord; for as much as ye know that your Labour is not in vain in the Lord.</hi> For as much as ye haſte unto, and draw nearer, and muſt be let into theſe continuing things, the inference here is Reaſonable and Natural, <hi>Wherefore Beloved, ſeeing that ye look for ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing Things,</hi> be diligent that your ſelves continue in the Service of the Lord. I ſay, ye look for continuing things, which is oppoſite unto periſhing things, as ſuch are all preſent things, and things of this World.</p>
            <p>I hope that none of ye do ſerve God for any viſible preſent Recompence as to thrive better in your Trades or Callings, and that ye are not in hopes to grow more Rich hereby and come to a place where his lively Word is declared, and his Spiritual Worſhip uſed out of any ſiniſter Reſpects and preſent Ends. If there was any thing to be got by it, what a Throng would be here? If ye do this, or the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike, ye will be miſtaken. <hi>For the Juſt ſhall Live by Faith.</hi> He will ſeek the Kingdom of God and his Righteouſneſs, and truſt that all theſe things ſhall be added unto it. The Terms we are to enter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods Service, is Grace here and Glory hereafter; neceſſary Accommodations for our Pilgrimage, and the true Reſt to come; the Patriark <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Requeſt, <hi>Bread to Eat and Raiment to put on;</hi> and all this is to be had only by Labour and Honeſt means, and no others. But when People come to ſerve the Lord, if they have thoughts of any more, and they do not find their Ends and Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions anſwered, then they leave off the Service of the Lord, which they would not have done, if they had known the Nature of God's Kingdom and the Way of his dealings towards the Children of Men. If there was a preſent Profit and Gain to be made by Religion, by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152398:20"/> every one that would try after it, then <hi>none would Fear God for nought,</hi> Job 1. 9. nor yet ſerve him for the alone Hope and Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of unſeen things. But People would traffick for Heaven, as they do to <hi>Jamaica</hi> or the <hi>Jndies,</hi> and all ſtill for the Love of themſelves, and not out of any Love to the Lord of that Countrey. What a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Mercenary Souls ſhould we have? Then the places of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or Hearing the Word of God, would be Flocked unto, even upon Week Days, as the <hi>Exchange,</hi> or as Country People go to Fairs and Markets, to Buy and Sell and get Gain. Then Worldly Minded Men would become the beſt Chriſtians. Thoſe who are all for themſelves, uſe Religion only now and then to ſerve a turn, or for a reſerve: But if there was any thing to be got at preſent by ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſuch would do moſt therein, and ſtill do nothing only for God's Sake. There would be then no <hi>Work of Faith,</hi> nor <hi>Labour of Love,</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t all Selfiſhneſs. But now, God hath moſt wiſely ordered it as it is, that the Trial of Faith might be had, that the Excellency of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience may be ſeen.</p>
            <p>But yet more clearly it will appear, how the right Underſtanding of the Nature of God's Kingdom and Dominion over Men, helps to make a continuing Work, from this Remarkable Scripture, <hi>Becauſe they have no changes. therefore they Fear not God,</hi> Pſal. 55. 19. My Soul hath much Meditated upon this Scripture, it being ſo very Applicable and Suitable to the People abroad in the World, for is not this the very Reaſon of the want of the Fear of God? or when they talk of it in a General Way, yet ſtill there is not that real Awe and Dread of God upon their Hearts, but there is a ſecret Contempt of him, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d a froward going on in the Way of their Hearts; as alſo a turning back from the Miniſtration of his Word. And all is, becauſe they have no changes, they ſee no odds, whither they do or do not. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in mine own private Prayer, every Morning and Evening, I have performed the ſame in a Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unctory, Haſty and Careleſs man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and ſometimes I have done it again more Solemnly, Awefully and Attentively. But I have obſerved no great matter of difference about the ſucceeding of my Actions the following day, whither I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed them in a due manner or not. Nay, Perhaps, It went more croſs and thwart when I was in the Morning before in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ervent Prayer, then when I was remiſs or negligent. And hereupon an evil Heart o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Unbelief hath aroſe in me, as if Prayers did ſignifie nothing; and there would be no great matter of difference, if they were ſaid meerly out of cuſtom or not at all. Is not this the very ſame as to other things pertaining to Religion? For do we ſee any odds or difference outwardly between <hi>him that Sacrificeth, or him that Sacrificeth not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Between them that go into the Sanctuary, or them that do not? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them who are conſtant hearers of the Word, or who deſpiſe the Word of the Lord, and refuſe to come to the place where it is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152398:21"/> forth or Preached. Themſelves ſometimes make a trial of both, and they find no changes, and therefore they are Confirmed more and more in their Ungodlineſs. Moab <hi>hath been at eaſe from his Youth, and he hath been ſetled on his Lees, and hath not been emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ied from Veſſel to Veſſel, neither hath he gone into Captivity; therefore his taste remained in him, and his ſcent is not changed,</hi> Jer. 48. 11. Even that <hi>Taſte</hi> and <hi>Scent</hi> of the Old Corrupt and Ungodly Nature. Now as to all this and ſuch like Imaginations in the Hearts of Men (for by Thoughts or Imaginations, every One is led guided and doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly) Here a right Underſtanding of the Nature of God's Kingdom and Dominion over us Men; How by the Ordering of things ſo as they are, he doth prove us, to know what is in our Hearts, whither we will keep his Commandments or no.</p>
            <p>By the way, any one may chooſe whither he will keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments or not, but then they muſt not chooſe unto themſelves that Eternal Life which God hath Promiſed to the keeping of them; nor yet may they chooſe or refuſe to avoid that Eternal Death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is annexed to the Contempt, Diſobedience and Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them.</p>
            <p>God hath alſo Ordained an Obedience of Faith, hath Permitted all things to happen alike unto all, an <hi>Hour</hi> of the Wicked, and the <hi>Power of Darkneſs,</hi> Luke 22. 53. Proſperity to the Sinners, Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to the Righteous. But above all, the Knowledge and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that all things ſhall be exactly ſo as they are ſpoken of in the Scriptures, this will engage and oblige People to continue in the Fear of the Lord, whither they have any <hi>changes</hi> or no; whither they be at <hi>eaſe from their Youth,</hi> or <hi>emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed from Veſſel to Veſſel,</hi> even however it is with People in this Life, and on this Earth. They that know and underſtand all theſe things, they will continue yet more fixedly, firmly and conſtantly in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear of the Lord; and that ſo much the more, as they ſee the day Approaching.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 23. Line 36. for ſomirk, Read Irkſom.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
